The world is changing
ان العالم يتغير
with really remarkable speed.
بسرعة كبيرة جداً
If you look at the chart at the top here,
ان نظرتم هنا على هذا التمثيل البياني
you'll see that in 2025,
سوف ترون انه في عام 2025
these Goldman Sachs projections
فان تنبؤات جولدمان ساكس
suggest that the Chinese economy
تقول ان الاقتصاد الصيني
will be almost the same size as the American economy.
سوف يصبح تقريباً بنفس حجم الاقتصاد الامريكي
And if you look at the chart
وان نظرتم الى التمثيل البياني
for 2050,
لعام 2050
it's projected that the Chinese economy
سوف ترون انه يظهر ان الاقتصاد الصيني
will be twice the size of the American economy,
سوف يصبح ضعف حجم الاقتصاد الامريكي
and the Indian economy will be almost the same size
والاقتصاد الهندي مقارباً للاقتصاد الامريكي
as the American economy.
على نحو واضح
And we should bear in mind here
ولكن يجب ان نأخذ بعين الاعتبار
that these projections were drawn up
ان هذه التوقعات كانت
before the Western financial crisis.
قبل الازمة الاقتصادية في الاسواق الغربية
A couple of weeks ago,
ومنذ اسبوعين
I was looking at the latest projection
كنت انظر الى التوقعات الجديدة
by BNP Paribas
التي صدرت من قبل بنك" بي ان بي بايباس "
for when China
والتي توضح
will have a larger economy
متى سوف يتجاوز اقتصاد الصين
than the United States.
اقتصاد الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
Goldman Sachs projected 2027.
فكانت توقعات جولدمان ساكس هي في عام 2027
The post-crisis projection
وتوقعات ما بعد الازمة هي
That's just a decade away.
اي بعد عقد واحد من الزمن
China is going to change the world
ان الصين سوف تغير العالم
in two fundamental respects.
في مفهومين اثنين اساسيين
First of all,
الاول
it's a huge developing country
هو انها دولة نامية عملاقة
with a population of 1.3 billion people,
بتعداد سكاني قدره 1.3 مليار نسمة
which has been growing for over 30 years
والتي كانت تنمو لمدة 30 عاماً
at around 10 percent a year.
بمعدل 10% كل عام
And within a decade,
خلال عقد واحد
it will have the largest economy in the world.
سوف تصبح الاقتصاد الاكبر في العالم
Never before in the modern era
اي انه لم يحدث من ذي قبل في العصر الحديث
has the largest economy in the world
ان كانت الدولة ذات الاقتصاد الاكبر في العالم
been that of a developing country,
من الدول النامية
rather than a developed country.
عوضاً عن كونها من الدول المتطورة
Secondly,
والامر الثاني
for the first time in the modern era,
هو انه لاول مرة في التاريخ الحديث
the dominant country in the world --
سوف تكون الدولة المسيطرة على العالم
which I think is what China will become --
والتي اظن انها الصين
will be not from the West
هي دولة تقع في الشرق .. لا في الغرب
and from very, very different civilizational roots.
وهي دولة ذات جذور حضارية مختلفة جدا جدا
Now, I know it's a widespread assumption in the West
وانا اعلم انه من الشائع في الغرب اعتقاد
that as countries modernize,
انه ما ان تتطور الدول
they also westernize.
حتى تكتسب شخصية الدول الغربية
This is an illusion.
ولكن هذا وهم
It's an assumption that modernity
إن افتراض ان الحداثة
is a product simply of competition, markets and technology.
يتم تشكليها فحسب من خلال المنافسة والاسواق والتكنولوجيا هو افتراض خاطىء
It is not. It is also shaped equally
لأنها تتشكل ايضاً
by history and culture.
بواسطة التاريخ والثقافة
China is not like the West,
ان الصين ليست دولة غربية
and it will not become like the West.
ولن تصبح دولة غربية
It will remain in very fundamental respects
وسوف تبقى بكل احترام
very different.
مختلفة جداً
Now the big question here is obviously,
والسؤال الكبير اليوم ..
how do we make sense of China?
هو كيف نفهم الصين ؟
How do we try to understand what China is?
كيف سيمكننا استعياب ما هية الصين ؟
And the problem we have in the West at the moment, by and large,
والمشكلة الشائعة اليوم على نطاق واسع
is that the conventional approach
في المقاربة الخاصة بتلك القضية
is that we understand it really in Western terms,
هي اننا نحاول ان نستوعب الامور من منظور غربي
using Western ideas.
وباستخدام افكار غربية
We can't.
وهذا خاطىء !
Now I want to offer you
الآن اريد ان اعرض عليكم
three building blocks
3 احجار اساس
for trying to understand what China is like,
لمحاولة استيعاب الصين
just as a beginning.
وكبداية
The first is this:
بداية كل هذا
that China is not really a nation-state.
ان الصين ليست " دولة قومية "
Okay, it's called itself a nation-state
لقد أسمت نفسها
for the last hundred years,
على مدى المئة العام الماضية
but everyone who knows anything about China
ولكن اي شخص يعرف الصين
knows it's a lot older than this.
يعرف انها اقدم من ذلك التاريخ بكثير
This was what China looked like with the victory of the Qin Dynasty
هذه هي الصين بعد انتصار سلالة " كوين "
in 221 B.C. at the end of the warring-state period --
في عام 221 قبل الميلاد .. بعد انتهاء عهد من الحروب
the birth of modern China.
انها ولادة الصين الحديثة
And you can see it against the boundaries of modern China.
وكما ترون ان الحدود مغايرة لحدود الصين اليوم
Or immediately afterward, the Han Dynasty,
وجاءت بعد ذلك حقبة سلالة الهان
still 2,000 years ago.
وايضاً منذ 2000 عام
And you can see already it occupies
وكما ترون .. لقد احتلت
most of what we now know as Eastern China,
معظم ما يعرف اليوم بالصين الشرقية
which is where the vast majority of Chinese lived then
والتي يعيش معظم الصينين فيها اليوم
and live now.
ويتكتل فيها العدد الاكبر من الصينين
Now what is extraordinary about this
والان ما هو الاستثنائي في هذا
is, what gives China its sense of being China,
انه .. ما يعطي مفهوم الصين ..
what gives the Chinese
انه ما تعنيه كلمة الصينين
the sense of what it is to be Chinese,
ان مفهوم الصين
comes not from the last hundred years,
لن يأتي من النظر الى المئة العام الماضية
not from the nation-state period,
ولا من فترة التسمية " كأمة قومية "
which is what happened in the West,
كما يحدث في الغرب
but from the period, if you like,
ولكن من الفترة ..
of the civilization-state.
التي كانت فيها دولة حضارة " ان صح التعبير "
I'm thinking here, for example,
يستحضرني الآن
of customs like ancestral worship,
الملابس الحربية القديمة
of a very distinctive notion of the state,
مفاهيم الدولة المميزة
likewise, a very distinctive notion of the family,
مفاهيم الاسرة المميزة
social relationships like guanxi,
العلاقات الاجتماعية مثل " جوانسي "
Confucian values and so on.
مفاهيم الحكيم " كونفوشيوس "
These are all things that come
واشياء كتلك
from the period of the civilization-state.
خرجت من عصر " دولة الحضارة "
In other words, China, unlike the Western states and most countries in the world,
لكي اوضح ذلك اكثر .. ان الصين ليست مثل الدول الغربية .. ولا مثل معظم دول العالم
is shaped by its sense of civilization,
فهي تشكلت بواسطة مفهوم الحضارة
its existence as a civilization-state,
بل انها وجدت بمفهوم الحضارة
rather than as a nation-state.
بدلا من ان تتشكل بمفهوم الدولة القومية
And there's one other thing to add to this, and that is this:
وهناك شيء آخر يمكننا اضافته الى هذا
Of course we know China's big, huge,
نحن نعلم حقاً ان الصين دولة كبيرة
demographically and geographically,
جغرافيا وديموغرافيا
with a population of 1.3 billion people.
بتعداد سكاني قدره 1.3 مليار نسمة
What we often aren't really aware of
وما لا نعيه عادة
is the fact
هو حقيقة
that China is extremely diverse
ان الصين متنوعة جداً
and very pluralistic,
وتعددية جداً
and in many ways very decentralized.
وهي لا مركزية على الاطلاق
You can't run a place on this scale simply from Beijing,
فلايمكن بسط سلطة " بكين - العاصمة - " على هذا الحجم الشاسع
even though we think this to be the case.
حتى لو كنا نعتقد ان هذا ما يحصل
It's never been the case.
انه لا يحصل مطلقاً
So this is China, a civilization-state,
حسناً .. هذه هي الصين .. دولة الحضارة
rather than a nation-state.
بدلاً من الدولة القومية
And what does it mean?
وماذا يعني هذا ؟
Well, I think it has all sorts of profound implications.
ان لهذا اثرٌ كبير
I'll give you two quick ones.
سوف اعطيكم اثنين من هذه الاثار
The first is that
الاول هو ان
the most important political value for the Chinese
اهم مفهوم سياسي للصينين هو
is unity,
الوحدة
is the maintenance
البقاء
of Chinese civilization.
للحضارة الصينية
You know, 2,000 years ago, Europe:
كما تعلمون فمنذ 2000 عام تعرضت اوروبا
breakdown -- the fragmentation of the Holy Roman Empire.
للتقسيم على يد الامبرطورية الرومانية
It divided, and it's remained divided ever since.
لقد قطعت .. وبقيت مقسمة منذ ذاك الحين
China, over the same time period,
والصين في هذه الفترة
went in exactly the opposite direction,
حصل لها العكس تماماً
very painfully holding this huge civilization,
محاولة الامساك والحفاظ على هذه الحضارة الكبيرة
civilization-state, together.
بالتوازي مع مفهوم الدولة
The second
والامر الثاني
is maybe more prosaic,
ربما هو مبتذلٌ جداً
which is Hong Kong.
وهو متعلق بهونغ كونغ
Do you remember the handover of Hong Kong
هل تذكرون تسليم هونغ كونغ
by Britain to China in 1997?
من البريطانين الى الصينين في عام 1997 ؟
You may remember
ربما تتذكرون
what the Chinese constitutional proposition was.
ماذا كان عرض الدستورين الصينين ..
One country, two systems.
بلد واحدة .. نظامين اثنين
And I'll lay a wager
وانا اراهن
that barely anyone in the West believed them.
ان الجميع في العالم الغربي صدق فكرة
"Window dressing.
ان بوجود نظام مستقل
When China gets its hands on Hong Kong,
عندما تندرج هونغ كونغ تحت سلطة الصين
that won't be the case."
لن يصبح الامر محورياً لهذه الدرجة
Thirteen years on,
بعد 13 عاماً
the political and legal system in Hong Kong
النظام السياسي والعدلي في هونغ كونغ
is as different now as it was in 1997.
مختلف كثيراً عما كان عليه في عام 1997
We were wrong. Why were we wrong?
لقد كنا مخطئين .. لقد اخطأنا
We were wrong because we thought, naturally enough,
لاننا ظننا ان الامر سيجري بمنظورنا
in nation-state ways.
في مفهوم الدولة القومية
Think of German unification, 1990.
كنا نتصور انه سيحدث ما حدث في المانيا عام 1990
What happened?
اتذكرون ما حدث
Well, basically the East was swallowed by the West.
عندما بتلع الغرب الشرق تماما
One nation, one system.
امة واحدة .. نظام واحد
That is the nation-state mentality.
هذه هي عقلية الدولة القومية
But you can't run a country like China,
ولكن هذه العقلية لا يمكن سحبها على الصين
a civilization-state,
انها امة حضارة
on the basis of one civilization, one system.
ان مبدأ حضارة واحدة .. نظام واحد
It doesn't work.
لا يفلح
So actually the response of China
ورد الصين على
to the question of Hong Kong --
قضية هون كونغ
as it will be to the question of Taiwan --
هو ذاته على قضية
was a natural response:
تايوان .. وهو رد طبيعي
one civilization, many systems.
حضارة واحدة .. عدة انظمة
Let me offer you another building block
دعوني اقدم لكم حجر اساس آخر
to try and understand China --
لكي نحاول فهم الصين
maybe not sort of a comfortable one.
ربما هي حجر أساس غريبة قليلاً
The Chinese have a very, very different
ان الصينين لديهم مفهوم مختلف جدا
conception of race
فيما يتعلق بالعرق
to most other countries.
مقارنة مع باقي الدول
Do you know,
هل تعلمون
of the 1.3 billion Chinese,
انه من بين 1.3 مليار شخص في الصين
over 90 percent of them
فان 90% منهم
think they belong to the same race,
ينتمون الى نفس العرق
the Han?
عرق " الهان "
Now, this is completely different
وهاذ مختلفٌ كثيراً
from the world's [other] most populous countries.
عن معظم الدول ذات الكثافة السكانية الكبيرة
India, the United States,
مثل الهند , الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
Indonesia, Brazil --
اندونيسيا , البرازيل
all of them are multiracial.
فكل هذه الدول تتكون من خليط اعراق
The Chinese don't feel like that.
بينما الصين .. ليست كذلك
China is only multiracial
ان الصين متعددة الاعراق
really at the margins.
في الاطراف المتناحية منها فحسب (الهوامش)
So the question is, why?
والسؤال هو .. لماذا ؟
Well the reason, I think, essentially
السبب هو اعتقد .. بصورة اساسية
is, again, back to the civilization-state.
انه بالعودة الى دولة الحضارة
A history of at least 2,000 years,
ربما بالعودة الى 2000 عام
a history of conquest, occupation,
الى عهد الاحتلالات والحروب
absorption, assimilation and so on,
والاندماج .. والاستيعاب
led to the process by which,
ان كل ذلك
over time, this notion of the Han emerged --
ادى عبر الزمن الى ان امة ال "هان " توسعت
of course, nurtured
بصورة طبيعية
by a growing and very powerful sense
بسبب قوتها وبسبب شعورها بالاستعلاء
of cultural identity.
وبالشخصية الثقافية الخاصة بها
Now the great advantage of this historical experience
وبالعودة الى التاريخ والى التجارب يمكننا انا نرى ان الفائدة الكبرى جاءت من فكرة
has been that, without the Han,
انه بدون سلالة الهان
China could never have held together.
ما كانت الصين لتبقى متماسكة كما هي
The Han identity has been the cement
ان الشخصية - شخصية سلالة الهان - كانت الرابط
which has held this country together.
الذي ربط هذه الدولة معاً
The great disadvantage of it
ولكن الامر الذي يعيب هذا الامر
is that the Han have a very weak conception
هو ان سلاسة الهان لديها مفهوم ضعيف جداً
of cultural difference.
عن التنوع الحضاري
They really believe
فهم يؤمنون حقاً
in their own superiority,
بعلوهم
and they are disrespectful
وهم لا يحترمون
of those who are not.
الآخرين الذين لا ينتمون الى سلالتهم
Hence their attitude, for example,
ومثالاً على ذلك يمكننا ان نرى تعاملهم
to the Uyghurs and to the Tibetans.
مع الإيغور .. ومع اهل التبت
Or let me give you my third building block,
سوف اخبركم عن حجر الاساس الثالث
the Chinese state.
للدولة الصينية
Now the relationship
ان العلاقة
between the state and society in China
بين الحكومة الصينية .. والمجتمع الصيني
is very different from that in the West.
هي مختلفة جداً عن تلك التي في الغرب
Now we in the West
نحن هنا في الغرب
overwhelmingly seem to think -- in these days at least --
مغبونون بالتفكير .. في هذا العصر على الاقل
that the authority and legitimacy of the state
ان السلطة والتشريع التي تحكم الدولة
is a function of democracy.
هي نوع من انواع الديموقراطية
The problem with this proposition
والمشكلة في هذه المقاربة
is that the Chinese state
هي ان الحكومة الصينية
enjoys more legitimacy
تتمتع بشرعية
and more authority
وسلطة
amongst the Chinese
بين الصينين
than is true
اكثر مما هي عليه
with any Western state.
الحكومات في الدول الغربية
And the reason for this
وسبب ذلك
is because --
هو انه ..
well, there are two reasons, I think.
في الحقيقة هناك سببين
And it's obviously got nothing to do with democracy,
وهما لا يتعلقان بالديموقراطية على الاطلاق
because in our terms the Chinese certainly don't have a democracy.
لاننا اذا اردنا ان نطبق شروطنا .. فان الصين لن تصنف من الدول الديموقراطية على الاطلاق
And the reason for this is,
وسبب هذا
firstly, because the state in China
الاول .. ان الدولة في الصين
is given a very special --
تتمتع
it enjoys a very special significance
بصورة مميزة جداً
as the representative,
بتمثيل شامل
the embodiment and the guardian
سواء كان لاعضاء البرلمان او الحكومة او البلدية
of Chinese civilization,
لجميع اشكال واطياف الحضارة \ الثقافة الصينية
of the civilization-state.
للدولة الصينية
This is as close as China gets
وهذا يقرب الوضع في الصين
to a kind of spiritual role.
إلى نوع من الدور الديني \ الروحاني
And the second reason is because,
والسبب الثاني
whereas in Europe
سواء في اوروبا ..
and North America,
او في امريكا الشمالية
the state's power is continuously challenged --
فان السلطة كانت على الدوام في موضع تحد\صراع
I mean in the European tradition,
اعني في التقاليد الاوروبية ..
historically against the church,
فالتاريخ يتحدث كثيراً عن صراع بين الكنيسة
against other sectors of the aristocracy,
والطبقة الارستقراطية
against merchants and so on --
وبين التجار
for 1,000 years,
لمدة 1000 عام
the power of the Chinese state
ان سلطة الدولة الصينية
has not been challenged.
لم تواجه اي تحد
It's had no serious rivals.
ولا اي ثورة هامة
So you can see
لذا يمكننا ان نرى
that the way in which power has been constructed in China
الطريقة التي تشكلت فيها السلطة في الصين
is very different from our experience
وهي مختلفة جداً عن الطريقة التي تشكلت فيها سلطتنا
in Western history.
في التاريخ الغربي
The result, by the way,
والنتيجة
is that the Chinese have a very different view of the state.
هي ان للصينين مفهوم مختلف جداً عن الحكومة \ السلطة
Whereas we tend to view it as an intruder,
فحين اننا نعاملها كدخيلة
a stranger,
او غريبة
certainly an organ
او ككيان
whose powers need to be limited
يحتاج ان تقوض سلطته
or defined and constrained,
او يتم تحديدها او تقيدها
the Chinese don't see the state like that at all.
فان الصينين لا يرون الامر على هذا النحو على الاطلاق
The Chinese view the state
ان الصينين ينظرون الى السلطة
as an intimate -- not just as an intimate actually,
كشريك .. ليس فحسب كشريك
as a member of the family --
انما كعضو من العائلة
not just in fact as a member of the family,
وليس فحسب كعضو من العائلة
but as the head of the family,
بل كرب للاسرة
the patriarch of the family.
عرابها
This is the Chinese view of the state --
هذه هي نظرة الصينين لحكومة الصين
very, very different to ours.
وهي مختلفة جداً عن نظرتنا
It's embedded in society in a different kind of way
وهي منغمسة - الحكومة - مع الشعب
to what is the case
بصورة مختلفة جدا
in the West.
عما هو الامر في الغرب
And I would suggest to you that actually what we are dealing with here,
واريد ان اطرح عليكم رؤيتي فيما نواجهه اليوم
in the Chinese context,
ضمن السياق الصيني
is a new kind of paradigm,
انه نموذج جديد
which is different from anything
وهو مختلف عن كل ما نعهده
we've had to think about in the past.
وعن كل ما كنا نعتقده
Know that China believes in the market and the state.
علينا ان نعلم .. ان الصين تؤمن بالسوق ,وبالدولة
I mean, Adam Smith,
اعني ان آدم سميث
already writing in the late 18th century, said,
كتب في اواخر القرن الثامن عشر
"The Chinese market is larger and more developed
ان السوق الصينية متطورة وكبيرة
and more sophisticated
وأكثر تنظيماً
than anything in Europe."
اكثر من اي سوق في اوروبا
And, apart from the Mao period,
بعيداً عن فترة " ماو "
that has remained more or less the case ever since.
والتي كانت القصة فيها مشابهة في حين .. او مختلفة في حين أخرى ..
But this is combined
ولكن على النسق العام
with an extremely strong and ubiquitous state.
بوجود دولة قوية جداً .. موجودة في نطاقات كثيرة
The state is everywhere in China.
ان حكومة الصين موجودة في كل مكان
I mean, it's leading firms --
اعني انها تقود الشركات
many of them are still publicly owned.
ان معظم الشركات هي شركات اهلية
Private firms, however large they are, like Lenovo,
والشركات الخاصة .. مهما كانت كبيرة .. مثل لينوفو مثلاً
depend in many ways on state patronage.
تعتمد بعدة طرق على معونات الحكومة
Targets for the economy and so on
ان الاهداف الاقتصادية ..
are set by the state.
تحدد بواسطة الحكومة
And the state, of course, its authority flows into lots of other areas --
والحكومة تمد سلطتها الى مجالات عدة
as we are familiar with --
نحن نعرف بعضها
with something like the one-child policy.
مثل سياسة انجاب طفل واحد فحسب
Moreover, this is a very old state tradition,
والاكثر من هذا وهو تقليد قديم جداً
a very old tradition of statecraft.
يتعلق بالانشاءات الحكومية
I mean, if you want an illustration of this,
اعني ان نظرنا الى صورة تلك الانشاءات ..
the Great Wall is one.
فاننا نرى ان سور الصين العظيم هو من معالمها
But this is another, this is the Grand Canal,
ولكن هناك معلم آخر .. انه القناة العظيمة
which was constructed in the first instance
والتي بدأ تأسيسها
in the fifth century B.C.
في القرن الخامس قبل الميلاد
and was finally completed
وانتهت تماماً
in the seventh century A.D.
في القرن السابع
It went for 1,114 miles,
انها تمتد على نحو 1114 ميلا
linking Beijing
تصل بكين
with Hangzhou and Shanghai.
بهانجزو و شنغهاي
So there's a long history
لذا هناك تاريخ طويل
of extraordinary state infrastructural projects
من مشاريع البنى التحتية الاستثنائية
in China,
في الصين
which I suppose helps us to explain what we see today,
والتي اعتقد انها تفسر ما نراه اليوم
which is something like the Three Gorges Dam
مثل ما شهدناه من افتتاح السدود الثلاث العظمى
and many other expressions
والعديد من المنشآت
of state competence
التي تمولها الدولة
within China.
داخل الصين
So there we have three building blocks
اذا هذه هي الاحجار الاساسية الثلاث
for trying to understand the difference that is China --
لمحاولة فهم الصين .. واختلافها
the civilization-state,
كونها امة حضارة
the notion of race
امة عرق واحد
and the nature of the state
وبطبيعة هذه الامة المختلف عنا
and its relationship to society.
وبعلاقتها مع المجتمع المختلفة عنا
And yet we still insist, by and large,
ورغم كل هذا وعلى نطاق واسع
in thinking that we can understand China
فاننا نظن اننا نستطيع استيعاب الصين
by simply drawing on Western experience,
عن طريق مقارنتها مع نموذج غربي
looking at it through Western eyes,
وان ننظر اليها بأعين غربية
using Western concepts.
وبمفاهيم غربية
If you want to know why
وان اردتم ان تعلموا لماذا
we unerringly seem to get China wrong --
نحن نستمر بفهم الصين بصورة خاطئة
our predictions about what's going to happen to China are incorrect --
وتوقعاتنا دائما مُخطئة في يحدث هناك
this is the reason.
في الحقيقة ان السبب
Unfortunately, I think,
للاسف كما اعتقد
I have to say that I think
وكما يتوجب ان اقول انه
attitude towards China
الانطباع تجاه الصين
is that of a kind of little Westerner mentality.
انه العقلية الاوروبية
It's kind of arrogant.
انها الغطرسة
It's arrogant in the sense
انها الشعور بالتفوق
that we think that we are best,
فنحن نظن اننا الافضل
and therefore we have the universal measure.
واننا المقياس العالمي
And secondly, it's ignorant.
وبصورة ثاني .. انه الجهل
We refuse to really address
فنحن نرفض ان نواجه
the issue of difference.
فكرة الاختلاف - بين الشرق والغرب -
You know, there's a very interesting passage
اتعلمون .. هناك فقرة مثيرة للاهتمام
in a book by Paul Cohen, the American historian.
في كتاب باول كوهين المؤرخ الامريكي
And Paul Cohen argues
يقول باول كوهين
that the West thinks of itself
ان الغرب يظن عن نفسه
as probably the most cosmopolitan
انه الثقافة الاكثر عالمية - التي يمكن تطبيقها على نطاق واسع -
of all cultures.
بين معظم الثقافات
But it's not.
ولكن ليس كذلك
In many ways,
في عدة مجالات
it's the most parochial,
انه الاكثر محدودية في الفكر
because for 200 years,
لانه على مدى ال200 عام الماضية
the West has been so dominant in the world
الغرب كان مسيطراً على العالم
that it's not really needed
سيطرة كانت لا تستوجب
to understand other cultures,
استيعاب وفهم حضارات ...
other civilizations.
وحضارات الآخرين
Because, at the end of the day,
لانها كانت تظن - الثقافة الغربية -
it could, if necessary by force,
انه يمكن ان تفرض طريقتها
get its own way.
بالقوة
Whereas those cultures --
حتى لو كنا نعني بالطرف الاخر
virtually the rest of the world, in fact,
كل الحضارات الاخرى الموجودة في العالم
which have been in a far weaker position, vis-a-vis the West --
والتي كانت على مدى طويل في موقع ضعف في مواجهة الثقافة الغربية
have been thereby forced to understand the West,
والتي اجبرت - الثقافة الشرقية - على استيعاب الغربية
because of the West's presence in those societies.
لان الغرب كان حاضراً في تلك المجتمعات
And therefore, they are, as a result,
ومن اجل ذلك .. وكنتيجة
more cosmopolitan in many ways than the West.
فان الحضارات الشرقية اكثر عالمية من تلك الغربية
I mean, take the question of East Asia.
اعني لنأخذ على سبيل المثال
East Asia: Japan, Korea, China, etc. --
اسيا الشرقية : اليابان , كوريا , الصين
a third of the world's population lives there.
ان ثلث العالم يعيش هناك
Now the largest economic region in the world.
وهي المنطقة الاقتصادية الاقوى في العالم اليوم
And I'll tell you now,
وسوف اخبركم
that East Asianers, people from East Asia,
ان الناس من شرق آسيا
are far more knowledgeable
يعرفون الكثير
about the West
عن الغرب
than the West is about East Asia.
مما يعرفه الغرب عن اسيا الشرقية
Now this point is very germane, I'm afraid,
وهذه النقطة هامة جداً
to the present.
للحاضر
Because what's happening? Back to that chart at the beginning,
بسبب ما يحدث اليوم .. اتذكرون المخطط البياني
the Goldman Sachs chart.
مخطط توقعات جولدن ساكس
What is happening
اترون ماذا يحدث
is that, very rapidly in historical terms,
بصورة سريعة - مقارنة مع التاريخ -
the world is being driven
ان العالم يتم قيادته
and shaped,
وتشكيله
not by the old developed countries,
لا بواسطة الدول المتقدمة
but by the developing world.
انما بواسطة الدول النامية
We've seen this
ونحن نرى هذا
in terms of the G20
في اجتماعات الدول ال 20 الكبرى
usurping very rapidly the position of the G7,
والتي تحتل بسرعة كبيرة موقع الدول ال 7 الكبرى
or the G8.
او مجموعة الثمانية
And there are two consequences of this.
وهناك عاقبتين لهذا
First, the West
الاولى .. ان الغرب
is rapidly losing
يخسر بسرعة كبيرة
its influence in the world.
تأثيره في العالم
There was a dramatic illustration of this actually a year ago --
وكان هناك تمثيل واضح لهذا في العام الماضي
Copenhagen, climate change conference.
وخاصة في كوبنهاجن في مؤتمر تغير المناخ
Europe was not at the final negotiating table.
ان اوروبا .. لم تكن موجودة على طاولة الحوار النهائية !
When did that last happen?
متي حدث هذا من ذي قبل ؟
I would wager it was probably about 200 years ago.
ربما منذ اكثر من 200 عام
And that is what is going to happen in the future.
وهذا ما سيحدث في المستقبل
And the second implication
والعاقبة الثانية
is that the world will inevitably, as a consequence,
هي ان العالم سوف يغدو .. كتبعة لما يجري اليوم
become increasingly unfamiliar to us,
سوف يغدو عالماً غريباً بالنسبة لنا
because it'll be shaped by cultures and experiences and histories
لانه يتم تشكيله بواسطة ثقافات وعادات وتاريخ
that we are not really familiar with,
نحن لا نعي شيئاً عنه
or conversant with.
او متجاهلين له ومتعنتين تجاهه
And at last, I'm afraid -- take Europe;
وفي النهاية انا متخوف بأن اوربا ..
America is slightly different --
ان امريكا مختلفة قليلاً
but Europeans by and large, I have to say,
ولكن الاوروبين .. على نطاق واسع
are ignorant,
متغطرسون
are unaware
و غير واعون
about the way the world is changing.
بالتغيرات التي تحصل في العالم اليوم
Some people -- I've got an English friend in China,
بعض الناس يقولون .. احدهم صديق بريطاني لي في الصين
and he said, "The continent is sleepwalking into oblivion."
يقول ان القارة العجوز تسير مغمضة تجاه النسيان
Well, maybe that's true,
ربما هذا صحيح
maybe that's an exaggeration.
ربما هذا مبالغ فيه
But there's another problem which goes along with this --
ولكن هناك مشكلة ايضاً تسير قدماً مع هذه المشكلة
that Europe is increasingly out of touch with the world --
هي ان اوروبا تبتعد من منآى العالم
and that is a sort of
وحس جراء فقد الاحساس
loss of a sense of the future.
بالمستقبل
I mean, Europe once, of course, once commanded the future
اعني ان اوروبا كانت في مرحلة ما تتحكم في المستقبل
in its confidence.
بكل ثقة
Take the 19th century, for example.
مثل ما كان يحدث في القرن 19
But this, alas, is no longer true.
ولكن هذا لم يعد صحيحاً
If you want to feel the future, if you want to taste the future,
وان اردت ان تشعر بالمستقبل .. ان تتذوق المستقبل
try China -- there's old Confucius.
عليك بالصين .. بكونفوشيوس القديم
This is a railway station
هذه محطة قطار
the likes of which you've never seen before.
انها شيء لم يرى مثله من ذي قبل
It doesn't even look like a railway station.
انها لا تبدو كمحطة قطار عادية
This is the new [Wuhan] railway station
انها محطة قطار جوانجزو الجديدة
for the high-speed trains.
للقطارات عالية السرعة
China already has a bigger network
ان الصين تملك اليوم اكبر شبكة سكك قطار
than any other country in the world
من اي دولة في العالم
and will soon have more than all the rest of the world put together.
وسوف تملك قريباً اكبر من مجموع كل السكك في العالم سويةً
Or take this: now this is an idea,
والان انظروا الى هذه الفكرة
but it's an idea to be tried out shortly
انها فكرة سوف تجرب قريباً
in a suburb of Beijing.
في ضواحي بكين
Here you have a megabus,
انها الباصات العملاقة
on the upper deck carries about 2,000 people.
انها تتسع ل2000 شخص على متنها
It travels on rails
وتتحرك على سكك
down a suburban road,
عبر الطرق الريفية
and the cars travel underneath it.
والسيارات تنتقل داخلها
And it does speeds of up to about 100 miles an hour.
وهي تسير بسرعة 100 ميل في الساعة
Now this is the way things are going to move,
وهذه هي الطريقة التي ستسير بها الاشياء
because China has a very specific problem,
لان الصين تملك مشكلة كبيرة
which is different from Europe
مختلفة عن اوروبا
and different from the United States:
وعن الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
China has huge numbers of people and no space.
ان الصين تملك عددا كبيرا من السكان .. ومساحة قليلة
So this is a solution to a situation
وهذا هو الحل لهذه المشكلة
where China's going to have
حيث ستطبق في الصين
many, many, many cities
في العديد والعديد من المدن
over 20 million people.
التي يتجاوز سكانها 20 مليون نسمة
Okay, so how would I like to finish?
حسناً كيف سأنهي هذه المحادثة
Well, what should our attitude be
كيف توجهنا يجب ان يكون
towards this world
تجاه العالم
that we see
الذي نراه
very rapidly developing
يتغير بسرعة كبيرة جداً
before us?
ويسبقنا بذلك ؟
I think there will be good things about it and there will be bad things about it.
اعتقد انه سيكون هناك ايجابيات وسلبيات لذلك الامر
But I want to argue, above all,
ولكن اريد ان اقول انه رغم هذا
a big-picture positive for this world.
يوجد صورة ايجابية للأمر .
For 200 years,
على مدى 200 عام
the world was essentially governed
لقد حُكم العالم بصورة اساسية
by a fragment of the human population.
قبل حفنة من البشر
That's what Europe and North America represented.
تقطن في اوروبا وامريكا الشمالية
The arrival of countries
وقدوم هذه الدول
like China and India --
مثل الصين والهند
between them 38 percent of the world's population --
واللتان تملكان 38% من سكان العالم
and others like Indonesia and Brazil and so on,
ودول مثل اندونيسيا والبرازيل
represent the most important single act
هذا سيعني التمثيل الديموقراطي
of democratization
الحقيقي
in the last 200 years.
ال200 عام
Civilizations and cultures,
للحضارات والثقافات
which had been ignored, which had no voice,
والتي كنا نتجاهلها .. والتي كانت صامتة
which were not listened to, which were not known about,
والتي لم يعلم احداً شيئاً عنها
will have a different sort
سوف اليوم تتمركز في مواقع جديدة
of representation in this world.
كممثلة للعالم
As humanists, we must welcome, surely,
وكبشر .. هم مرحبون بهم تماماً
this transformation,
وبهذا التغير
and we will have to learn
وعلينا ان نتعلم
about these civilizations.
فيما يخص هذه الحضارات
This big ship here
ان السفينة العملاقة هذه
was the one sailed in by Zheng He
هي التي ابحر بها " زينج هي "
in the early 15th century
في بدايات القرن 15
on his great voyages
في رحلاته الكبيرة
around the South China Sea, the East China Sea
عبر البحر الصيني الجنوبي .. والشرقي
and across the Indian Ocean to East Africa.
وعبر المحيط الهندي الى شرق افريقيا
The little boat in front of it
والقارب الصغير أمامها
was the one in which, 80 years later,
هو الذي صنع بعد 80 عام
Christopher Columbus crossed the Atlantic.
والذي ابحر فيه كريستوفر كولومبوس عبر الاطلنطي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or, look carefully
والان انظروا جيداً
at this silk scroll
على هذه الرسمة الحريرية
made by ZhuZhou
التي صنعت بواسطة " زو زو "
in 1368.
في عام 1368
I think they're playing golf.
اعتقد انهم يلعبون لعبة الغولف
Christ, the Chinese even invented golf.
يا إلهي .. الصينين أيضاً اخترعوا الغولف !
Welcome to the future. Thank you.
اهلاً بكم في المستقبل .. شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)